Hello, child! I'm Grandma Sankofa. Come with me, way back in time.
More, more, even more, before the cell phone, before the TV, before the book, before the writing, before the school, 3,200,000 years ago.
Here she is, Lucinha. She is 4 years old. She lives in Ethiopia, in the east of the African continent, and she has a special thing.
Look, look well, Lucinha is standing, on her two feet, walking. Lucinha is one of the first girls we know who walked upright in our great and ancient family.
Before her, many millions of years ago, other children also walked upright, in Chad, in Kenya, in Ethiopia.
But Lucinha is the most famous of all. A little girl, 3 million years ago, walking in the African savannah.
Shall we sing to me, Lucinha?
Do you know how we know about Lucinha? Scientists, people who study the past, found her bones, in 1974, in Ethiopia.
And do you know the name they gave her? Lucy, because of a Beatles song that played in the camp.
Do you know something? Every time you walk on foot, every time you run, jump, dance, you are doing what Lucinha started, 3 million years ago.
She is part of our very ancient family, from all over the world.
Do you remember my name? Sankofa. It is an ancient word from the people of Akan, in Ghana.
It means, come back, go, look, come back in time, look for history.
Learn with those who came before, you are part of this story, child.
Bye. Walking on foot is a very ancient thing. I am the bones. Sankofa.
See you next time.